Guide to the Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.) collection, 1836-1990 UA.01.02.0002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.) collection
1836-1990.
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. University Archives
UA.01.02.0002
20.3 Linear Feet
In 1841, Trinity College in Randolph County, N.C. was first formally chartered as Union Institute formed by the Union Institution Society, a group of Methodists and Quakers. Braxton Craven became head of the institution in 1842. The school was rechartered in 1851 as Normal College, and its graduates were licensed to teach in the public schools of the state. In 1859, the name of the institution changed to Trinity College upon affiliation with the Methodist Church. John Franklin Crowell became president of Trinity College in 1887; Trinity College relocated to Durham, N.C. in 1892. This artificial reference collection consists of photocopies of correspondence, diaries, printed material, and articles dealing with Union Institute, Normal College, and Trinity College in Randolph County, N.C. English. Included are account books accounts of student "tuition & contingency," bible, book, boarding fees, paper, and ink purchases. Several volumes include the signatures of students. Roll books contain students' names, courses, attendance, assignments, and grades. Accounting for faculty fees and payments are also included.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisitions Information
The source and provenance for this collection cannot be traced.
Historical Note
Trinity College began as Brown's Schoolhouse in Randolph County, N.C., a private subscription school led by Brantley York, who became the principal in 1838. A year later, Brown's Schoolhouse was formally organized by the Union Institution Society, a group of Methodists and Quakers. In 1841, the State of North Carolina issued a charter for Union Institute, turning it into an academy. In 1842, Braxton Craven became head of the institution. The school was rechartered in 1851 by the Legislature of the State of North Carolina as Normal College, and its graduates were licensed to teach in the public schools of the state. In 1859, the name of the institution is changed to Trinity College upon affiliation with the Methodist Church.
Scope and Contents note
This artificial collection consists of photocopies of correspondence, diary excerpts, printed material, articles, account books (ledgers), roll books, gradebooks, and official records pertaining to Union Institute, Normal College, and Trinity College in Randolph County, N.C.
Included are account books accounts of student "tuition & contingency," bible, book, boarding fees, paper, and ink purchases. Several volumes include the signatures of students. Roll books contain students' names, courses, attendance, assignments, and grades. Accounting for faculty fees and payments are also included.
Related Material
Enoch Faw diary, 1851-1857.
Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library, Duke University.
Catherine E. Hanes papers, 1861-1873.
Southern Historical Collection (#1959-z), University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.
Robert Philip Howell memoirs, 1854-1872.
Southern Historical Collection (#4045), University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.
William M. Jordan papers, 1913-1882.
Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library, Duke University.
William McKendree Robbins papers, 1836-1905.
Southern Historical Collection (#4070), University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.
Education -- North Carolina -- History -- 19th century; Quakers -- North Carolina -- History; Methodist Church -- North Carolina -- History; Randolph County (N.C.) -- History; Teachers colleges -- North Carolina; Craven, B. (Braxton), 1822-1882; Crowell, J. Franklin (John Franklin), 1857-1931; Union Institute (Randolph County, N.C.); Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.); Normal College (Randolph County, N.C.); Duke University -- Students; Duke University -- History
- Normal College, Postmarks and Logos, undated-1895 (Box 1)
- Normal College, North Carolina Annual Conference of Methodist Church, 1851, 1856 (Box 1)
- Becton Family, Correspondence (Box 1)
- Trinity College, Class of 1880, W.A. Jones Papers (Box 1)
- Memoirs, Long, Augustus W. (Box 1)
- Articles and Clippings, 1885-1936 (Box 1)
- Diaries and Notebooks, Amanda Simons, circa 1860-1870 (Box 1)
- Sneed, Walter Letter (Box 1)
- Sermon to the Theological Society of Trinity College, undated (Box 1)
- Historical Accounts and Materials, circa 1859-1988 (Box 1)
- Reminiscences Index (Box 1)
- Trinity College Advertisements (Box 1)
- Trinity College Announcements (Box 1)
- Articles and Clippings, 1950-1990, undated (Box 1)
- Bulletins and Supplements, 1887-1892 (Box 1)
- Cherokee Indians (Box 1)
- Tributes to Craven, 1882 (Box 1)
- Trinity College Circulars (Box 1)
- Trinity College Forms (Box 1)
- Trinity Magazine, A College Monthly, Vol I (duplicates) (Box 1)
- Trinity Magazine, A College Monthly, Vol II (duplicates) (Box 1)
- Trinity College Publications, Number 1, Lessons from Our North Carolina Records (Box 1)
- Trinity College Publications Numbers 1, 2 and 3, 1889-1891 (Box 1)
- Normal College Handouts (Box 1)
- Sesquicentennial Program, 1988 (Box 1)
- Union Institute Constitution, Minutes and Accounts, 1839-1853 (Volume 1)
- Normal College Account Book, 1853-1859 (Box 2)
- Record of Normal College, 1853-1855 (Box 2)
- Trinity High School (Randolph County) Records, 1891-1892 (Box 2)
- Account Book of Student Fees and Payments, 1845-1848 (Box 3)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes loose receipts for student purchases from the American Bible Society and Its Auxilliaries.
- Student Roll Book, with grades, 1850-1853 (Box 3)
- Account Book of Student Fees and Payments, 1854-1856 (Box 3)
- College Roll Book, with grades, tuition, fees and payments, 1855 (Box 3)
  Ledger is incomplete, and missing its cover boards.
- Notes Due Book, with lists of notes due to Trinity College, 1859-1864 (Box 3)
  This volume contains student lists arranged by county. Also included are Bonds of Students, also arranged by county.
- Teaching Staff Account Book, including operations expenses, 1859-1861 (Box 3)
  Ledger also includes accounting of projects such as building a book desk, and school operation expenses.
- Account Book, Number 3 with Student Fees and Payments, 1860-1861 (Box 4)
- Account Book, Number 4 with Student Fees and Payments, 1860-1861 (Box 4)
- Account Book, Number 5 with Student Fees and Payments, 1860-1861 (Box 4)
- Account Book, Number 8 with Student Fees and Payments, and Invoices and Receipts for School Operations, 1860-1861 (Box 4)
  Includes invoices, receipts, and 'promise to pay' paper slips that are pasted into the book.
- Account Book, Number 11 with Student Fees and Payments, 1860-1861 (Box 4)
- Account Book Tracking Books Loaned, 1861-1866 (Box 4)
- Muster Roll of Military Department with Student Grades, Fees and Payments, 1861-1864 (Box 4)
- Account Book with Student Fees and Payments, 1861-1896 (Box 5)
- Faculty Account Book with Expenses and Payments, and Class Syllabi, 1866 (Box 5)
- Autograph Book with Student Signatures, Professions, and Personal Quotes, 1866-1872 (Box 5)
- J.R. Pierce, Notes on Rhetoric, 1870 January 16 (Box 5)
- Roll Book with Student Names, Attendance and Grades, 1870 (Box 5)
- Trinity Building and Loan Association Bank Stock Book of Monthly Payments, 1872 (Box 5)
- Treasurer's Book for Trinity Building Association, with Dues, Deposits and Reports, 1872 February 29 (Box 5)
- Account Book with Student Fees and Payments, 1872-1882 (Box 6)
- General Order with Student Names, Attendance, Assignments and Grades, 1875 September 2 (Box 6)
- Declamations Book with Student Names, Classes, and Grades for Speeches, 1878 (Box 6)
- Class Book with Student Names, Grades, and Household Tasks, 1879 Sep 3 (Box 6)
- Account Book of Student Fees and Payments, 1879 September 3 - 1880 June 10 (Box 6)
- Account Book of Student Fees and Payments, 1879 September 30 - 1880 June 12 (Box 6)
- Roll of Trinity College after it reopened, 1866-1869 (Box 7)
- Clippings (Box 8)
- Leaflets and Broadsides, 1866-1882 (Box 8)
- Student Lists and Grades, 1858-1880s (Box 8)
- Minutes and Resolutions [Normal College], 1851-1859 (Box 8)
- Official Papers, 1852-1882 (Box 8)
- Commercial Drafts, undated (Box 8)
- Annual Reports, 1858-1882 (Box 8)
- Insurance Papers, 1870-1880 (Box 8)
- Account Papers, 1868-1872 (Box 8)
- Student List (damaged, fragile), 1870s (Box 10)
- Gradebook (damaged, fragile), 1876-1877 (Box 10)
- Financial records, 1856-1859 (Box 10)
- Financial records, 1860-1869 (Box 10)
- Financial records (3 folders), 1870-1879 (Box 10)
- Financial records, 1880-1882 (Box 10)
- Receipt, 1886 (Box 10)
- Account Books (include faculty and student book and supply accounts), circa 1870s (Box 11)
- Account Books, 1870s (Box 12)
- Account Books, 1870s (Box 13)
- Account Book, 1870 (Box 14)
- Account Books, 1880-1881 (Box 15)
- Student ledger, 1871-1872 (Box 16)
- Account book, 1885 (Box 16)
- Account book, 1891-1892 (Box 16)
- Trinity College Society of Alumni, circa 1858-1873 (Box 17)